My name is Hagoromo...
As the founder of Ninshu,
the Ninja Creed...
I am also known as
The Sage of the Six Paths.
You're The Sage of
the Six Paths?
(ハゴロモ)名を ハゴロモ。
Indeed I am.
忍宗の開祖にして
六道仙人ともいう。
Right now, Naruto and
Sasuke have taken on
(柱間)あなたが六道仙人!?
Ashura and Indra's souls and
are battling my mother Kaguya...
いかにも。
Ashura?
今 ナルトとサスケは
アシュラとインドラの魂を引き継ぎ→
You just called me
the "previous reincarnate"?
Yes...
Ashura and Indra are my two sons.
我が母 カグヤと戦っている。
アシュラ!?
And Kaguya, the one who's
fighting right now, is my mother.
たしか 今 私を前任者と…。
What?!
そうだ。 アシュラとインドラは
わしの２人の息子…。
So Ashura and Indra's souls
are connected to you too.
そして 今 戦っている カグヤは
わしの母だ。
Their souls have transmigrated
over and over again.
なんと！
The soul of Ashura was
previously inside you,
アシュラとインドラの魂は
お前にも関係のあることだ。
and Indra's soul was inside Madara.
(ハゴロモ)
２つの魂は転生を繰り返し➡
Inside of me?!
Mother took advantage
of their souls,
以前 アシュラの魂は お前に…。
and after an extraordinary
length of time,
インドラの魂は
マダラに宿っていたのだからな。
she was resurrected.
Right now, I know everything,
(柱間)私に!?
even the intentions of
the one called Zetsu,
(ハゴロモ)母上は ２人の魂を利用し→
my mother's third son
who possessed Madara.
途方もない時間を使って
よみがえったのだ。
In order to save
Naruto and Sasuke,
今 わしには
マダラにとりついていた→
you, too, must know everything
that has occurred.
ゼツと名のる 母上の第３の息子の
意思まで すべて わかる。
Before I talk about
Ashura and Indra,
I must first explain the origin
of Ninshu, the Ninja Creed.
ナルトとサスケを救うには➡
お前たちも
すべてを知る必要があるのだ。
It was a few thousand years ago...
アシュラとインドラの話をするには➡
My younger brother Hamura and I,
まず 忍宗の起源から
話さねばなるまい。
sealed our mother Kaguya and
the Ten Tails in the moon.
(ハゴロモ)時は 数千年の昔。
わしと 弟のハムラは
母上のカグヤと十尾を月に封印した。
Hamura went to the moon as well,
so he could watch over Mother.
そして ハムラは 母上を見張るため
月へと渡っていったのだ。
aimaina hyouden koshiraete hitatteru no
I create a vague critical biography and wallow in it
seisei saisai nani o mada matteru no
Generation after generation, time after time,
what are you still waiting for
itsunomanika hitori ni natta
I was all alone before I knew it
tameiki hitotsu haite nageite
Breathed out a single sigh and lamented
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosunda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
en de tsunagareba kono hibi mo
Bind these days with bonds and perhaps
suteru hodo koware tenaidarou
They can be salvaged
ayumi o tomenaide
Don't stop walking forward
kibou o sutenaide
Don't give up hope
douka furimuite
Please look back
dou ka kimiyo
Please, if you would
jin jin kokoro ga itamunara
If the heart throbs with pain
kannen no ori o uchiyaburu nda
Break through the ideology that imprisons you
enen tsukihi wa megurukedo
Time goes around for eternity
suteru ni wa yami ga asaidarou
But the darkness within you is still shallow,
not worth throwing it all away
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosu nda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
ai o wakeaeba kono hibi mo
If we love each other then surely these days will
mouichido kimi o terasudarou
Once again, shine upon you
Ninshu: The
Ninja Creed
Thank you for your help, Gamamaru.
Without the Sage Power
that you taught me,
we couldn't have defeated Mother.
You insist on leaving, brother?
Yes. There is something I must do.
((ハゴロモ : 世話になったな ガマ丸。
(ハゴロモ)お前に教えてもらった
仙力がなければ→
What are you going to do?
My journey will have two purposes.
母上は倒せなかった。
(ガマ丸)どうしても行くのか 兄弟。
The first...
あぁ。 私には
やらねばならぬことが ある。
To find a dwelling place for each
of the nine Tailed Beasts
that I extracted from
the Ten Tails.
(ガマ丸)何をするつもりじゃ？
I want to make sure
they don't fight amongst each other...
(ハゴロモ)旅の目的は ２つ。
and that people don't use
their powers for evil.
１つは 十尾から分けた
９匹の尾獣の住みかを探すことだ。
I intend to choose
their homes very carefully.
The second purpose is to
restore this ravaged land.
この連中が
互いに ケンカをせぬよう➡
その力が人々に悪用されぬよう→
In our battles against Mother,
慎重に故郷を見定めようと思う。
we caused terrible damage
to the land.
２つ目の目的は→
I must atone for this crime.
この荒れ果てた地上を
復元することだ。
I see.
母上との戦いで 私たちは
地上に莫大な傷を残してしまった。
Yes, that might be good to do.
But the road ahead will be difficult.
I am aware of that.
私は その罪を
償わなければならない。
You know,
I had a dream last night.
そうか…。
A dream?
Toads rarely dream.
そうじゃのう
それが いいかもしれん。
When they do dream,
it always comes true.
だが 道は厳しいぞ。
わかっている。
Because a toad's dream
is destiny.
実は 昨日 夢をみた。
夢？
What did you dream?
Far into the future,
a blue-eyed youth will appear,
ガマは めったに夢をみぬ。
みた夢は 必ず現実となる。
who will amuse himself with
the names of the nine beasts.
ガマの夢は運命じゃからのう。
I dreamed that
he will call forth a miracle.
どんな夢だ？
Does that mean there will be
another age of discord?
遠い未来に ９匹のケダモノの名を呼び
たわむれる 碧眼の少年が現れる。
I do not know.
Will everything I do from now on,
be meaningless?
Don't worry.
その子が奇跡を呼び起こす夢じゃ。
Fate is something
you cannot escape.
再び 乱世が
やってくるというのか？
わからぬ。
では 私が
これから やることも ムダか？
Go on your way.
気にする必要は ない。
And if fate wills it,
our paths shall cross again, brother.
避けようと思って 避けられるのは
運命などでは ないからのう。
Farewell.
お前は お前の道をいくとええ。
縁があったら
また会おうぞ 兄弟。
うむ さらばだ。
I guess this is my first test.
Huh?
どうやら１つ目の試練のようだな。
Hey, hey, hey, hey!
What are you doing?
I'm going to fix the bridge.
What?
Why do something uncalled for?
(フタミ)おい おい おい おい
何してんだ？
How is it "uncalled for"?
The bridge is essential
to everyone.
橋を直すのさ。
Everyone needs it.
は？ お前
なに余計なことしてんだよ。
That's why it's a problem
for me if it's there.
Oh... An interesting comment.
なぜ余計だ？
橋はみんなにとって必要なはずだ。
Listen, because the bridge
is broken,
みんなにとって必要だから
俺には あっちゃ困るのよ。
everyone stops right here.
That's where I come in.
I go over to the guy
and take his belongings
ほう おもしろいことを言うな。
and offer to help him cross.
いいか この橋が壊れてるから→
Then, without a moment's hesitation,
みんな ここで立ち止まる
そこで俺の出番だ。
I make my getaway
with his stuff.
I may not look fast,
but these legs never fail me.
そいつのもとに行って
俺がこの川を→
This is what I do for a living.
無事に渡してあげましょうと
荷物を預かる。
I see.
そしたら すたこらさっさと
逃げちまうのさ。
So you're a thief that uses
this broken bridge to make a living.
こう見えても
足には自信があるんだ。
That's right.
So just leave well enough alone.
それが俺の商売よ。
フフ なるほど お前は
この壊れた橋で食っている→
But it only benefits you.
It's a hardship for everyone else.
泥棒というわけか。
そうよ。
Hey! I said leave it alone.
Do you understand me?
だから 余計なことされると
困るのさ。
だが 橋を直して
困るのは お前一人だ。
多くの人は困らない。
てめえ やめろって言ってんのが
わからねえのか。
Why are you going through
all that trouble?
This is to atone for my sins.
うっ…。
So are you a criminal?
Something like that.
なんで お前
そんなことするんだよ？
私は罪を償っている。
Oh man, I guess can't
cross the bridge.
お前 罪人なのか？
Mister, you seem to be in a bind.
似たようなものだ。
Leave it to me,
I'll take you to
the other side of the river.
なんだ この橋は渡れないのか。
- Oh!
- I wouldn't, if I were you.
That man's a thief.
旦那 お困りのようですね。
What?!
ですが あっしに任せてくれれば
川の向こうへお渡ししますぜ。
Don't take me for a fool!
おぉ。
よすのだな。
Hey, you!
その男は泥棒だ。
なっ…。
Quit messing with my business!
俺をバカにするな。
I'm not moving until
I fix this bridge.
You should go find
another bridge.
おい てめえ！
人の商売の邪魔するんじゃねえ。
Don't be stupid!
Thieves like me have
our own territory...
チッ…。
I can't just go somewhere else.
私は この橋を直すまで
ここを動かん。
Well then,
why don't you help me?
別の橋に行ったほうがいいぞ。
I'll leave once the bridge
is finished.
バカ言え 俺たちにも縄張り
ってもんがあるんだよ。
Quit messing around!
他のとこになんて行けるか。
I see.
Then there's nothing more to say.
では どうせなら
手伝ったらどうだ？
You can wait until
the bridge is fixed.
橋が完成すれば 私はよそへ行く。
ふざけたこと言ってんじゃねえ！
そうか ではしかたない。
そこで橋が直るまで待つのだな。
うぉっ…。
Damn it!
Fine, I'll just get in his way...
That bastard...
チクショウ こうなったら邪魔して…。
Just where does that
brute strength come from?
う～ん！
あの野郎…。
どんなバカ力してやがんだ。
Damn it!
Hey! Get it together!
We've got to work fast or the logs
you went to great lengths to gather
will just get washed away.
あ～ もう！
Oh...
You're going to help me?
I just want you to go away
as soon as possible.
(フタミ)おい しっかりしやがれ！
急がねえと せっかく集めた材木が
流されちまうぞ！
And once the bridge is done,
I'm gonna destroy it.
ほう 手伝ってくれるのか。
My name is Hagoromo.
And I'm Futami.
俺はさっさと あんたに
どっかに行ってもらいたいんだ！
Nice to meet you, Futami.
橋ができたら 俺が
ぶっ壊してやる！
フフッ。
私の名前は ハゴロモだ。
(俺は フタミだ。
よろしくな フタミ))
Ouch!
What are you doing?
Can't you tell?
I'm building a bridge!
You're a thief, right?
Doing that won't make all
the bad stuff you did go away!
Shut up! Get lost, brat!
((イテッ！
何やってんだよ？
見てわかんねえのか？
橋をつくってんだよ。
Now, you're just like me.
お前 泥棒だろ？
そんなことしても→
I'm not like you.
悪さしたことは消えないぞ！
うるせえ！
I'm not doing this
for atonement.
どっか行け このガキ！
I'm telling you...
When it's done,
I'm gonna destroy it.
ハハハ これでお前も
私と同じだな。
同じなもんか。
俺は罪を償ってるわけじゃねえ。
橋ができたら
絶対にぶっ壊してやる！
All that work and we're only
one-third of the way done...
Breaking it apart is easy,
but building it back up
is backbreaking work.
Something this sturdy
won't be easy to break.
やっと３分の１かよ。
That's true.
If we make it too sturdy...
壊すのは簡単だが
つくるのは骨が折れる。
you'll break your bones for sure
when you try to destroy it.
こんだけ丈夫につくり直せば
そう簡単には壊れないぜ。
そうだな だが
あまり頑丈につくりすぎると→
Hey you! Don't touch those logs!
We're using 'em to fix the bridge!
お前が壊すときに
骨が折れるぞ。
We'll help you.
え？ ヘヘ。
Huh?
Since we're going to be
the ones using the bridge.
おい コラ
かっぱらうんじゃねえ！
You gotta be careful.
そいつは橋をつくる
材料なんだからな！
Just grab a smaller one.
Okay!
俺たちも手伝います。
え？
だって俺たちが使う橋ですから。
ったく 危なっかしいなあ。
もっと小さいのにしろ。
うん。
It's finished!
We did it! We did it!
The bridge is finished!
This is awesome!
It's done, eh?
やった やった やった～！
A bridge worth the effort to destroy.
橋が完成したぞ！ アハハ！
Are you kidding me?!
After all the work we put into it,
there's no way I'd destroy it.
うお～ すげえ！
完成したな。
You did a good thing.
壊しがいのある橋だ。
And it's time for me to move on
to a new place.
何言ってんだ
こんな苦労してつくったのに→
Take care of yourself, Futami.
ぶっ壊せるわけねえだろ！
ハハハ！
お前は よいことをしたな。
私は新たな地へ
向かうときがきたようだ。
Hey, wait up!
達者でな フタミ。
I'm coming with you!
Oh?
I thought that bridge
was where you lived.
With an awesome bridge
like that,
おい 待ってくれよ！
俺も一緒に行くよ。
my business is shot to hell!
ほう あの橋が
お前の住みかではないのか？
When you do a good deed,
people are grateful and
it's a good feeling.
あんな立派な橋が出来たんじゃ
俺の商売は あがったりだぜ。
And because it feels good,
you do more good deeds.
That's the cycle of goodness.
よき行いをすると
人々に感謝されて気分がいい。
When you put it that way...
you're right.
You have a way with words.
そして気分がよくなるために
更に よいことをする。
By the way,
I didn't ask you before, but...
それが よき行いの輪廻だ。
Who are you anyway?
確かに… そう言われればそうだ。
あんた いいこと言うな。
I once wreaked havoc
upon this world.
そういや
ずっと聞けなかったけど→
Several years ago,
there were many occurrences
あんた いったい何者なんだ？
of giant tsunami and
volcanic eruptions here and there.
Don't tell me you caused them?
私はかつて
この世界をめちゃくちゃにした。
Come on, there's no way
one person could've done that!
何年か前に あっちこっちで→
大津波や大噴火が
立て続けにあったけど→
Besides, if you were that strong,
you could've fixed that
bridge in an instant,
まさか それが
あんたのせいだっていうのか？
instead of working and
sweating so hard.
I decided never to use
excessive power again.
そんなことが
人にできるわけねえだろ。
それに そんな力があるなら→
Otherwise, I wouldn't be able
to understand how people feel.
さっさと
橋を直せばいいじゃねえか。
Put your hand out.
あんなに汗水流さなくても。
私はもう
余計な力は使わぬと決めた。
そうでなければ
人々の心はわからぬ。
What is this?
I feel power surging into me.
手を出してみろ。
え？
I just passed my power to you.
Power?
Yes...
Or maybe I should say chakra.
何だこれ… 力が湧いてくる。
It is, so to speak, the power to
connect people to each other.
That's the kind of power
I want it to be.
今 お前に力を渡したのだ。
力？
And you passed it on to me?
そうだな チャクラとでも呼ぼうか。
Yes. But it's not something
I can give to just anyone.
いわば 人と人をつなぐ力だ。
I've come to feel
very close to you.
そういうものであってほしいと
私は願っている。
You have learned
what a good heart is.
俺は それをもらったのか？
そうだ だが誰にでも
分け与えられるものではない。
What are you doing?
お前の心が私に近くなったからだ。
Please, make me your apprentice!
お前は善の心を知ったのだ。
My apprentice?
Yeah!
I feel something very special
in you...
I've lived a meaningless life.
何のマネだ？
俺を あんたの弟子にしてくれ。
My entire life's been worthless!
But you're different.
弟子だと？
あぁ。
You're someone who
can do great things!
あんたには
何か特別なものを感じる。
So... if I stay with you,
俺は ずっと
つまらない人生を生きてきた。
maybe my insignificant life will
start to show a little value.
何の価値もねえ人生だ。
だけど あんたは違う。
So you want to be helpful
to others now?
あんたは きっと
大きなことを成し遂げる人だ。
When we finished that bridge...
だから あんたといれば
俺のチンケな人生も→
All those happy people
and their smiles...
I've never been prouder
in my whole life.
ちょっとくらい
価値が出ると思うんだ。
I'll never forget the look
on their faces!
人の役に立ちたくなったか。
I'm positive that that's the bond
that you spoke of...
あの橋をつくったことは→
あのとき
喜んでくれた人たちの笑顔は→
I mean, Master Hagoromo.
俺の生涯の誇りだ。
あのときの
みんなの顔が忘れられねえ。
You just taught me something
very important.
きっとそれが あんた…
いえ ハゴロモ様の言った絆だ。
I think my journey has found
another important purpose.
A third purpose.
お前は私に
大きなことを教えてくれた。
People bonding through chakra.
私の旅には もう１つ
大きな目的ができたようだ。
３つ目の目的
チャクラによる人々の絆だ。
Mister, hey Mister!
You in a bind because
the bridge is broken?
I can help you cross
to the other side...
Hey, you!
What are you doing here?!
This is my turf!
(ミツオ)旦那 旦那
橋が壊れててお困りでしょう。
We're going to rebuild this bridge!
あっしが向こう側へ渡る方法を…。
Huh? What the hell are you saying?
お前 なんで こんなところに!?
Listen up!
From today, you're gonna
become a good person!
ここは俺の縄張りだぞ！
Did you hit your head
or something?
今から この橋をつくり直すぞ。
は？ なに言ってんだ この野郎。
いいから！ 今日から
お前も善人になるんだよ。
In time, albeit slowly...
I found people who understood
my way of thinking.
お前 頭おかしくなったのか？
(フフフフ… ハハハハハハハ！))
And some among them joined me
on my journey to help people.
(ハゴロモ)やがて 徐々にだが
人々の中にも→
わしの考えを
理解しようとする者たちが現れた。
From around this time,
I made them my apprentices...
その中には わしとともに
人々のために→
and passed on my chakra.
一緒に旅をしてくれる者たちまで
現れるようになった。
I named this bond
"Ninshu, the Ninja Creed."
この頃から わしは
その者たちを弟子とし→
I trained with my apprentices...
自分のチャクラを分け与えていった。
and continued to ponder...
そして その絆を わしたちは
忍宗と名付けた。
What is life? What is love?
わしは弟子たちとともに修業し
考え続けた。
What is power?
We believed that someday, this bond
with people through chakra
命とは何か。 愛とは何か。
NINSHU
would lead to world peace.
力とは何なのかを。
We continued our travels
for a long time.
わしたちは いつか
チャクラでできる人の絆が→
Restoring places that were
nearly destroyed for no reason...
世界を平和に導くと信じたのだ。
And when we found a place
in those areas
わしたちの旅は果てしなく続いた。
where we could release
the Tailed Beasts,
途方もなく荒れ果てた地を
直しながら…。
we built a shrine for the purpose
of guarding them.
(ハゴロモ)そして その中で→
尾獣たちを解放するための
場所を見つけては➡
Many of my pupils scattered
to different regions
そこに
監視のための祠をつくった。
to repair the land in my place.
And in this manner, Ninshu,
the Ninja Creed, spread to
each corner of the world.
(ハゴロモ)弟子たちの多くは→
荒れ地を
わしの代わりに修復するため➡
And later, on my deathbed,
各地へと散っていった。
I sent the Tailed Beasts that had been
inside me to their respective lands.
こうして忍宗は
世界の各地に広まっていったのだ。
Praying that they would be able
to spend their days in peace...
その後 わしは 死の間際→
自分の中にいた尾獣たちを
彼らの故郷に放った。
I will not live much longer...
Shukaku, Matatabi, Isobu,
Son Goku, Kokuo,
彼らが平穏に暮らせる日々が
やってくることを祈りながら。
Saiken, Chomei, Gyuki, and Kurama...
((私は もう長くない。
Even if you are far apart,
you will always be together.
守鶴 又旅 磯撫 孫悟空→
And eventually,
there will come a time
when you will be united again.
穆王 犀犬 重明→
Each of you with a unique name...
and a different form
than before.
牛鬼 九喇嘛。
離れていても
お前たちはいつも一緒だ。
And unlike when
you were inside of me,
いずれ一つになるときが来よう。
you will be guided down
the right path.
I hope you learn
what true strength is...
それぞれの名を持ち
今までとは違う形でな。
before that time...
そして 私の中にいたときと違い
正しく導かれる。
本当の力とは何か。
But as you know,
contrary to my hopes...
(そのときまで))
Throughout this long history,
men appeared one after another,
with the desire to use
Tailed Beasts for evil purposes...
(ハゴロモ)しかし
お前たちも知ってのとおり→
which turned the Tailed Beasts
against mankind.
わしの思いとは裏腹に→
長い歴史の中で尾獣たちの力を➡
Anyway, back to my story.
悪用しようとする者たちが
次々と現れ→
We continued our long journey.
When at last,
I fulfilled my three goals,
彼らは人間に
愛想をつかしてしまうのだが…。
I returned to my village
話を戻そう。
and made it the headquarters
of Ninshu.
わしたちは 長い旅を続け→
ようやく３つの目的が
ひと段落し→
I married and fathered two sons.
村に戻ったわしは
その地を忍宗の総本山とした。
They were Indra and Ashura.
Their mother had a difficult recovery
after giving birth to Ashura...
わしは そこで妻をめとり
２人の子供を授かった。
and she passed away
shortly after.
それが インドラとアシュラだ。
But my two sons grew up
strong and healthy.
They were close siblings.
アシュラを産んでから ２人の母は
産後の肥立ちが悪く→
The older one was especially caring
まもなく この世を去った。
and the younger one was always
chasing after his brother.
しかし
２人の息子は元気に育った。
２人は仲のよい兄弟だった。
But at the time, I didn't realize
兄は常に弟を思い→
弟は常に 兄の背を追いかけた。
that a dark force
was already at work
trying to manipulate my sons...
(ハゴロモ)だが わしは このとき
まだ気づいていなかった。
息子たちを利用しようと→
すでに闇の力が
うごめきはじめていたことに。
kaze ga fui te iku
The wind is blowing
yoru o mata yorokete aruku
I stagger through the night
butsukatte koron de shippai bakkashite
Colliding, falling, and failing
make sou ni naru kedo
I'm always about to lose
warawaretatte ii yo kanarazu umaku iku sa
Go ahead and laugh, I'll figure out a way
gomen ne datte ieru
I'm even willing to say I'm sorry
nakitai nakitai nakitai kurai ni
Until we feel like crying and crying
kirei na tsuki no shita uta o utaou
Let's sing a song under the pretty moonlight
donna ni kuradanai sekai datte ii yo
It doesn't matter how awful the world is
setsunai setsunai rarabai kurai ni
Like a sad, sad lullaby
mune ga kurushikute mo hecchara na no sa
even if it hurts inside, it won't bother us
naki sou naki sou naki sou na hodo
Until we're about to cry and cry
yasashii uta datte arun dakara
There will always be a gentle song
At the time,
my Ninshu did not have
a practical application for fighting yet.
My original intent for it was
to help bring souls together.
But due to Indra's innovations,
the course of Ninshu
was drastically changed.
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"Ashura and Indra"
He was one who was worthy
of being called the "Genius of Ninshu."